10/30/24  AC 61-65J 
  Appendix A 
A-14 A.39 Flight proficiency/practical test: º 61.65(a)(6). 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required training of º 61.65(c) 
and (d). I have determined they are prepared for the Instrumentû[airplane, helicopter, or powered -lift] practical test.  
A.40 Prerequisites for instrument practical tests: º 61.39(a).  
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received and logged the required flight time/training of º 61.39(a) in preparation for the practical test within 2 calendar months preceding the date of the test and has satisfactory knowledge of the subject a reas in which 
they were shown to be deficient by the FAA Airman Knowledge Test Report. I have determined they are prepared for the Instrumentû[airplane, helicopter, or powered- lift] 
practical test.  
FLIGHT INSTRUCTOR (OTHER THAN FLIGHT INSTRUCTORS WITH A SPORT 
PILOT RATING) ENDORSEMENTS  
A.41 Fundamentals of instructing knowledge test: º 61.183(d) . 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required fundamentals of instruction training of º 61.185(a)(1) . I have determined that they are prepared for the 
Fundamentals of Instructing knowledge test. 
A.42 F light instructor aeronautical knowledge test: º 61.183(f). 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required training of º 61.185(a)[(2) or (3) (as appropriate to the flight instructor rating sought)]. I have determined that they are prepared for the [name of] knowledge test. 
A.43 Flight instructor ground and flight proficiency/practical test: º 61.183(g). 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required training of 
º 61.187(b) . I have determined that they are prepared for the CFI û [aircraft category and 
class] practical test.  
Note: T he endorsement for a practical test is required in addition to the º 61.39 endorsements provided in endorsements 1 and 2 (see paragraphs A.1 and A.2). 
A.44 Flight instructor certificate with instrument û(category/class) rating/practical test: 
ºº 61.183(g) and 61.187(a) and (b)(7). The endorsement for a practical test is required in addition to the º 61.39 endorsements provided in endorsements 1 and 2 (see paragraphs A.1 and A.2). 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required certificated flight 
instructor - instrument training of º 61.187(b)(7). I have determined they are prepared for 10/30/24  AC 61-65J 
  Appendix A 
A-15 the certificated flight instructor - instrumentû[airplane, helicopter, or powered- lift] 
practical test.  
A.45 Spin training: º 61.183(i)(1). The spin training endorsement is only required of flight 
instructor airplane and flight instructor glider applicants. 
I certify that [First name, MI, Last name] has received the required training of º 61.183(i) 
in [an airplane, a glider]. I have determined that they are competent and possess instructional proficiency in stall awareness, spin entry, spins, and spin recovery procedur
